<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Erick Martins Ratamero, Ph.D.</title>
<link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Erick Ratamero&#39;s blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.53</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>My August project: Boku no Natsuyasumi 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="playing-boku-no-natsuyasumi-2-every-single-day-in-august-has-been-a-delight." class="level1">
<h1>Playing Boku no Natsuyasumi 2 every single day in August has been a delight.</h1>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-04 19_12_51-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Meeting people is hard."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-04 19_12_51-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Meeting people is hard."></a></p>
<figcaption>Meeting people is hard.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you’ve never heard of Boku no Natsuyasumi (My Summer Vacation): it’s a very popular series of games in Japan, where the basic premise is that you are a young child going to spend your (titular) summer vacation somewhere. You can think of it as Animal Crossing-adjacent: you explore a cute location, interact with the people living there, catch some fish and some bugs, and so on. There’s a day-night cycle, certain things are only available at certain times, you know the drill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-28 15_08_17-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="The Akane house in Fumi became my second residence for August."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-28 15_08_17-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The Akane house in Fumi became my second residence for August."></a></p>
<figcaption>The Akane house in Fumi became my second residence for August.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>None of the Bokunatsu games saw a western release, ever. (the newer stuff from the same studio, Millenium Kitchen, is available, though.) It’s one of those series that people who are deep enough into the rabbit hole that is gaming talked about without full context, and western folks who can speak Japanese raved about. And then, a group of <em>extremely</em> dedicated fans carefully put together an English translation of Bokunatsu 2. I cannot say enough glowing things about the work they’ve done here, both in terms of the quality of the prose itself and the absolute technical marvel that this translation is. For example, the original game has vertical text; they somehow converted that into a horizontal textbox at the bottom of the screen.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-07 14_44_04-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="You do get to open this gate if you want to."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-07 14_44_04-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="You do get to open this gate if you want to."></a></p>
<figcaption>You do get to open this gate if you want to.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ll get this out of the way: Boku no Natsuyasumi 2 is wonderful. It’s a small miracle. It’s warm, gentle, thoughtful, and just a tiny little bit sappy at times. It made me feel nostalgic for rural Japan in the 70s, a time and space I had very little knowledge about.</p>
<p>So the game starts and it’s August 1st, 1975. You’re a 9-year old kid named Boku (I know), taking the ferry to Fumi, a tiny little community somewhere in Japan. Your mom is about to give birth to a child, and your parents sent you over to stay with your aunt and uncle in Fumi so you don’t need to be around for that. That’s it. This is all you’re given. There are no objectives, no tutorials, nothing you need to do. You’re a kid on vacation, staying in a small village with your extended family and the locals. Have fun. You’ll have breakfast and dinner with your family at set times, and you have a limit for your bed time. Those are the only limitations.</p>
<p>I love how open-ended everything is. There were many things that I’ve certainly missed, some things I only discovered when it was too late to do them properly, and so on. It’s a game that clearly doesn’t expect you to see everything in a single playthrough, and getting rid of that minmaxing bug in your brain is a good thing here. In just a few in-game days, I was able to let go of the instinct to optimize and just enjoy being a weird kid running around this village.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-31 16_42_22-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="I genuinely have no idea if this scene always happens or if some of the stuff I did made it happen."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-31 16_42_22-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="I genuinely have no idea if this scene always happens or if some of the stuff I did made it happen."></a></p>
<figcaption>I genuinely have no idea if this scene always happens or if some of the stuff I did made it happen.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Boku is a wonderful protagonist - the way this kid is written and voiced made me smile all the time. Boku is a kind-hearted, curious, very funny kid, who asks good questions and likes teasing people. But he’s very much a kid. He doesn’t understand some things even when you, the player, does; there’s nothing you can do in-game to change that. You are not Boku.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-10 18_21_48-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Gramps had some stuff to take off his chest."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-10 18_21_48-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Gramps had some stuff to take off his chest."></a></p>
<figcaption>Gramps had some stuff to take off his chest.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Now for some added fun: as I said, this is a game that starts on August 1st, 1975. Following a friend’s suggestion, I decided to play one in-game day per real-life day. It didn’t end up mapping one to one for a number of reasons, but I did my best. I know there’s no such thing as the right way to play a game but honestly? This might be the right way to play this game. If you’re in the northern hemisphere. And you live in a place with seasons. The reminders that summer is ending in-game synchronizing with the first slightly chillier days where I am worked really, really well. Everyone’s mood shifts as fall is starting to peek around the corner: the people in the game and myself. It also helps that each day takes about half an hour if you’re playing on the default speed. It’s a totally reasonable time commitment for a daily task, right there with my crosswords.</p>
<p>The one thing I’m divided on is whether to do this again next year. One one hand, I would love to go back to Fumi, see the things I didn’t see, do the things I didn’t do. But at the same time, I love where Boku’s story ended at. This month of August felt like <em>my</em> version of what Boku’ August would have been, and to some degree going back to it would just undermine its power by making me optimize more, focus less on enjoying the scenery and the people in the village. Ultimately, I worry that re-experiencing August 1975 would make this month less unique.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-12 11_36_36-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Boku loves to sit at a place and just vibe."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-12 11_36_36-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Boku loves to sit at a place and just vibe."></a></p>
<figcaption>Boku <em>loves</em> to sit at a place and just vibe.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>video games</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/bokunonatsu2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OME Community Meeting 2024 round-up</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="ome-community-meeting-2024---what-happened-there" class="level1">
<h1>OME Community Meeting 2024 - what happened there?</h1>
<p>So as a first real blogpost I decided it was a good idea to write a quick recap/summary of what happened during the <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/events/ome-community-meeting-2024/">OME 2024 Community Meeting</a> - it’s both a pretty easy write for me and potentially helpful for other folks out there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="PXL_20240529_073549219.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Did you know there’s a Lemmings statue in Dundee?"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/PXL_20240529_073549219.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Did you know there’s a Lemmings statue in Dundee?"></a></p>
<figcaption>Did you know there’s a Lemmings statue in Dundee?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="so-what-is-this-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-what-is-this-meeting">So what is this meeting?</h2>
<p>Probably a good place to start is explaining <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/index.html">OME</a> - according to themselves,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>a consortium of universities, research labs, industry and developers producing open-source software and format standards for microscopy data.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In practice, it’s a community of like-minded tool developers who write things that are 1) open-source; 2) dealing with microscopy data; 3) uses the <a href="https://ome-model.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">OME data model</a> to some degree - and the users of such tools. In the past (i.e.&nbsp;pre-pandemic), this was a relatively large meeting (100-200 people is my guess?), with lots of end-users presenting their use cases.</p>
<p>Post-pandemic, this survived in a kinda-barebones, virtual-only format for a few years, until May this year, when we finally managed to meet in person again, in lovely Dundee, Scotland. Even better, I was invited to give a talk! (for the record, this is the second time ever I had an proper invited talk, and the first time I managed to be there to actually give it.). Though much smaller than previous meetings (attendance was around 45 people), most of the big names are core developers were there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="PXL_20240528_100142225.PANO.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="the day before the conference, I climbed a hill"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/PXL_20240528_100142225.PANO.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="the day before the conference, I climbed a hill"></a></p>
<figcaption>the day before the conference, I climbed a hill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="now-a-quick-recap-per-day" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="now-a-quick-recap-per-day">Now a quick recap per day</h2>
<section id="day-0-speakers-dinner" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-0-speakers-dinner">Day 0: speakers’ dinner</h3>
<p>So the day before the actual meeting, the people giving invited talks had the chance to have dinner together - it’s the kind of informal opportunity to network and enjoy each other’s company that is really hard to replicate virtually, and after 5 years without in-person meetings, it was great to see many familiar faces! We also had a LOT of tapas. I did not take pictures, so you’ll have to believe me.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-1-bioimage-data-resources-and-community" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-1-bioimage-data-resources-and-community">Day 1: BioImage Data Resources and Community</h3>
<p>This was the main “conference day” - invited talks from all over the world, about how institutions and cross-institutional entities are involved in the OME ecosystem. This is where we (i.e.&nbsp;The Jackson Laboratory folks) gave our invited talk, and essential projects around OME (such as <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/bio-formats/">Bio-formats</a> and the <a href="https://idr.openmicroscopy.org/">IDR</a> gave community updates.</p>
<p>The big takeaway in my opinion was that large national entities, such as German Bioimaging, France Bioimaging and NL-Bioimaging, are deeptly invested in OME. Similarly, large public data repositories also rely heavily on the tools the data models of the OME environment; not only the IDR, but also things like the Bioimage Archive and SSBD. These entities have a mix of either centralized and distributed infrastructure, and very different ideas for what metadata standards should look like, making harmonization between these disparate cases pretty hard.</p>
<p>Still, some common themes have emerged, such as the <em>desire</em> to have common metadata standards, and a convergence towards using OME-Zarr as the file format for the future. We are seeing, for example, multiple efforts for processing OME-Zarr using Slurm/HPC have emerged (such as the awesome <a href="https://fractal-analytics-platform.github.io/">Fractal</a>). The day ended with very good food (you’ll start to sense a theme here) at <a href="https://www.dca.org.uk/experience-dca/eat-and-drink-at-jute/">Dundee Contemporary Arts</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-2-training-on-omero-and-workshops" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-2-training-on-omero-and-workshops">Day 2: Training on OMERO and Workshops</h3>
<p>For the first half of day 2, we had a few more talks, focusing on using <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/omero/">OMERO</a> in training settings - it included an initially funny, but then just awesome story about a collaboration with an Indonesian university, which was unwittingly “abusing” the demo OMERO server provided by the University of Dundee to teach pathology classes to medical students. The “abuse” was discovered and, instead of just cutting them off, a partnership was developed, and now Dundee hosts a separate server for the Indonesian folks.</p>
<p>The second half of day 2 was dedicated to workshops - we had breakout rooms with a few scheduled sessions, and an extra room for impromptu/ad-hoc sessions. The sessions I attended had a lot of Zarr talk, including the first discussions of a “Dundee Pledge” - an attempt to align the folks in the room around a set of practices and tools that would allow for easily extensible metadata. Again, the day ended with excellent food - this time, at an Indian place whose name escapes me right now.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-3-unmeeting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-3-unmeeting">Day 3: Unmeeting</h3>
<p>Day 3 was a half-day, scheduled to end at lunchtime. It was “organized” as an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference">unmeeting</a> - participants decided what the agenda of day 3 would be at the beginning of the day. What ended up happening was a lot of work and discussion around what eventually became the <a href="https://forum.image.sc/t/ome2024-ngff-challenge/97363">OME2024 NGFF Challenge</a>.</p>
<p>So what is that? In brief, in Josh Moore’s words,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>converting some significant corpus of day (e.g., 1 PB) using what we think the next version of OME-Zarr (e.g., including sharding, collections, etc.) will be by the end of September.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s an ambitious plan: it involves fast-forwarding some specifications in a pretty speculative way, coordinating multiple entities and institutions, and herding cats in a very short timeframe. The plan is to, very quickly, demonstrate that this is a viable way of going in the future, and speed up tool development in some areas. Excitingly, since as part of the challenge multiple institutions agree on a (<em>very</em>) minimal metadata standard, that means a single front-end can index and search data that exists in many different storage sources, paving the way for a future where public data repositories can be fully federated.</p>
<p>Since then, multiple working groups have made quick progress, and in two days we are hitting the date where specifications for the challenge will enter a freeze. That will give people time to get their tooling in order, and to actually convert the data they will provide for the challenge. Needless to say, we at JAX will be taking part in it, planning to offer around 50TB of Zarr files to it.</p>
<p>I am told this day ended with a scotch tasting - I had an early plane to catch and ended up skipping it.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-about-next-year" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-about-next-year">What about next year?</h3>
<p>The idea is to continue in-person meetings for next year - folks in the US have soft-committed to organizing it this side of the pond next year. We’re still looking for a location (probably on the East Coast), but there’s already work being done towards that!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>I think it’s fair to say this was the most <em>intense</em> (and probably the best) scientific meeting I have ever attended - the fact that this is very much the niche where I spend most of my time, and the relatively small size of the meeting, meant that every waking hour was spent having meaningful, important discussions. You’d go for breakfast and other folks would be there, already talking shop. Then you’d spend the whole day at the conference, then have dinner at the conference, then go grab drinks with the conference folks. Of course, there was plenty of time for less-professional talk as well, but but you still had to be “on”. I am VERY excited for next year already - especially if it ends up being in our backyard!</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>OME</category>
  <category>OMERO</category>
  <category>Conference</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/ome-logomark.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
