<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Erick Martins Ratamero, Ph.D.</title>
<link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Erick Ratamero&#39;s blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.53</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The Senna series on Netflix is the most weightless way you could tell the Senna story.</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-25-senna-netflix/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><em>Senna</em>, the Netflix series, is a huge deal in Brazil. It’s Netflix dumping a truckload of money into a production that has Brazilian writers, Brazilian directors, Brazilian producers, (mostly) Brazilian actors. No TV series in Brazil has ever been this expensive.</p>
<p>I really, really wanted to like this. And, in many ways, this is a success: it’s a well-made, well-crafted miniseries produced for an international market. I bet it will attract a lot of eyeballs and be a commercial success (whatever that means for Netflix). I bet it will win some awards. But, about two episodes into this 6-parter, I had to start writing down my thoughts on this. The TL;DR: they spent 170 million dollars on a shiny piece of TV that has nothing interesting to say about its subject.</p>
<p>I’m not going to spend any time talking about Ayrton Senna and his story - if you are an F1 fan you know that by heart, if you are not, wikipedia is right here for you. The legend of Senna is as alive 30 years after his passing as it has ever been. His death, traumatic and untimely, froze the man and the driver in time: the Senna in people’s minds today is the same as it was in 1994, if not even more sanctified.</p>
<p>Which is to say I understand this series being a hagiography. What else could you do, really? The mythologized sports story is a well-traveled road, the production involved Senna’s family directly, a budget this big can’t be put into anything but. And Senna’s story fits the mold particularly well.</p>
<p>Still: I will get on my soapbox real quick about Netflix’s <em>Drive to Survive</em> and its nefarious influence over sports documentaries. <em>Drive to Survive</em> didn’t do anything new: its particular brand of creating “safe drama” (i.e.&nbsp;superficial conflict without deep stakes), its insistence in framing its subjects as “good guys” regardless of reality, none of that is novel. Reality TV has been doing that for decades in very similar contexts. Storytelling is millenia old etc etc. I know. But it feels like the massive success of <em>Drive to Survive</em> has somewhat warped the landscape of what people feel is possible in the sports documentary-ish space, in particular around F1, and I can’t avoid seeing some of that here (at the risk of doing a <a href="https://x.com/afraidofwasps/status/1177301482464526337">boss baby vibes</a>). Yes, Senna was a notoriously prickly person who had beef with a few characters. That is depicted in the series, but the stakes never feel real, never feel heavy; part of it seems to be a deliberate choice to never stew on the times Senna lost. Whole seasons of frustration and defeat are put into a “two years later” card so we can move on to the next success. We see Senna angry at times, but we never see him defeated.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="sonic.webp" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="We also never see Senna holding the Sonic Trophy, which is a shame."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-25-senna-netflix/sonic.webp" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="We also never see Senna holding the Sonic Trophy, which is a shame."></a></p>
<figcaption>We also never see Senna holding the Sonic Trophy, which is a shame.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Even his biggest moments of elation feel somewhat weightless: say, for example, the 1991 Brazilian GP win. The stuff of legends. Genuinely one of the greatest F1 performances of all time. And some of that does come across in the series; but without the context, without knowing Senna had qualified first in Brazil the three years prior and had lost those races through bad luck, and crashes, and all sorts of weirdness, that incredible moment of finally winning his home grand prix under the weirdest possible circumstances feels emptied. It makes his “tinha que dar” comment afterwards, “it had to work this time”, feel meaningless. It robs what is probably one of the greatest sporting moments of all time of its power.</p>
<p>And here’s the thing: it still hits <em>for me</em>, because I have that context. It hits for me, as lots of things in this series do. If you are a Brazilian F1 fan of a certain generation, this is incredible nostalgia bait. They did a fantastic job recreating <em>everything</em> to be period perfect, from the cars and the sponsors to, like, what the TV broadcast graphics looked like. The casting is genuinely incredible, with an great array of F1 driver lookalikes and the best Galvão Bueno Impersonator they could find. Kaya Scodelario’s Portuguese is surprisingly very very good, even though I am not sure what her character is and why she’s here. The races are very well shot, particularly when they don’t go into CGI fuckery. The craft is all there. It’s just they… decided to tell a story a lot of people already know, in a boring way.</p>
<p>Then there’s all the things they very pointedly decided <em>not</em> to touch. Senna’s relationship with a 15-year old. Senna’s support for a shitty right-winger for the São Paulo Mayorship. It’s a hagiography, I get it. Senna’s family has a hand in the production. It’s their choice not to talk about the Bad Stuff - but the Bad Stuff is part of who the man was, it’s part of the story. It’s more than just ignoring the bad stuff, though: there’s a definite effort here to paint Senna as a Man Of The People, which is, in my opinion, laughable. He’s never been that - he was born wealthy, grew up like that, has always been that. F1 has also never been what’s been depicted in the series for us Brazilians. Yes, it was very popular at the time, in the sense that people would wake up early on Sundays to watch it, and Senna was one of the most famous people in the country, no question. But people were not decorating their streets and doing Senna Watch Parties. That’s World Cup stuff in Brazil. It happens once every four years. Interlagos’ stands didn’t look like the Maracanã; even back then, F1 tickets were extremely expensive and only the (very small at the time) middle class could afford it. Senna was, by all accounts, a charitable man, yes, a Brazilian idol, for sure; but not a man of the people. Never was.</p>
<p>Funny enough, the best five minutes of the series are the last ones: when they show actual documental footage and actual pictures from all the moments the series covered, and you realize how far they went in trying to recreate things one-to-one (in particular, it made me remember the intro scene of episode 4, when Senna goes to Xuxa’s children’s show on TV, was 100% accurate in its absurdity). Many times during this, I caught myself thinking it would have been way cooler if they just inserted the original footage right then, during a particularly important moment. There’s this specific shot of lap 6 in Imola 1994 that immediately made me shudder because I know it deep inside me to be the exact TV shot right before they cut to the camera that will capture the crash. And they recreated the specific camera angle, everything, to the degree that my body reacted to the recreation instictively. Why dump all that money into one-to-one recreations? Why not use the archival footage instead? I think it would have grounded the whole thing, brought it back to earth, and made it feel less like an exercise in craft, and more like the real story it was.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>tv</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-25-senna-netflix/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-25-senna-netflix/senna.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>These are some games I’ve played in 2024</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Cohost is dead, long live cohost. Last year I wrote a post <a href="https://cohost.org/ratamero/post/3754778-in-which-i-talk-abou">there</a> talking about every game I played in 2023. If you are reading this in 2025, that link does not work anymore. So here we are, and now I have my own blog that I write on infrequently - so I might as well use it for writing about every game I’ve played in 2024.</p>
<section id="games-that-came-out-in-2024" class="level1">
<h1>Games that came out in 2024</h1>
<section id="final-fantasy-vii-rebirth" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-fantasy-vii-rebirth">Final Fantasy VII Rebirth</h2>
<p>I think FFVII Remake, the game before this one, was the most pleasant surprise I’ve had with a game in a long, long time. It felt like an impossible project: remaking one of the most beloved games ever. They somehow pulled it off, making something that was simultaneously very close to the original and an interesting, original story, which opened up so many cool possibilities for whatever came next.</p>
<p>What came next was this, pardon my french, wet fart. A bloated, confused mess of a game. A game where nothing happens for 100h, and then you get the most lukewarm, middle-of-the-road conclusion possible. They could have done literally anything with this game, and they chose to do nothing. The worst kind of checklist game. It’s very rare that I get genuinely angry at a video game, but this one managed to do it. Multiple times.</p>
</section>
<section id="animal-well" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="animal-well">Animal Well</h2>
<p>There was a little chunk of the year there where a bunch of cool, interesting, puzzle-adjacent games came out in short succession. Animal Well was one of them. It’s a cute puzzle-platformer with incredible art, and then it’s more, way more. I did not go all the way into the rabbit hole (a lil joke here for the people who played Animal Well), and stopped when I felt satisfied, and that took me about 15h. Not an easy game, but very, very interesting and worth playing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="Animal_Well_disc.webp" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="you play as a certified little guy (the meatball-looking dude there)"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/Animal_Well_disc.webp" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="you play as a certified little guy (the meatball-looking dude there)"></a></p>
<figcaption>you play as a certified little guy (the meatball-looking dude there)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="balatro" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="balatro">Balatro</h2>
<p>Playing Balatro this year was mandatory. I did not play nearly as much as most people did, for sure; Probably less than 10h. It did not really have staying power for me, and the infinite-roguelike-keep-trying-until-you-get-a-good-run is very much not for me, and the way certain parts of the internet talk about it in terms of “addiction” rub me very much the wrong way (especially for a game with a lot of gambling-adjacent imagery). Still, it’s undeniably a very cool idea extremely well executed, for better or worse. Definitely a game I preferred to admire from a distance.</p>
</section>
<section id="lorelei-and-the-laser-eyes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="lorelei-and-the-laser-eyes">Lorelei and the Laser Eyes</h2>
<p>This was completely out of left field for me. This studio pivoted from the very cool action-rhythm game Sayonara Wild Hearts to… a puzzle game? And a really good one? This game looks absolutely INCREDIBLE, has a genuinely interesting story that went places I did not expect (in a very, very positive way), and hit a difficulty level with its puzzles that was just right for me - a good mix of “you can solve this easily as soon as you find the relevant info” and “you might need some slightly lateral thinking to understand what’s being asked”. Maybe on the level of, say, a moderately difficult escape room; also, very much like an escape room, it is a game that gives you ALL the relevant info to solve its puzzles, even when there’s a reasonable argument to be made that most people know about it (though I guess I am being unkind to folks who do not know Roman Numerals).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="lorelei.webp" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="tfw the magician gives you a bunch of symbols"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/lorelei.webp" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="tfw the magician gives you a bunch of symbols"></a></p>
<figcaption>tfw the magician gives you a bunch of symbols</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="duck-detective-the-secret-salami" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="duck-detective-the-secret-salami">Duck Detective: The Secret Salami</h2>
<p>This is a cute, largely inoffensive little thing. It’s very clearly inspired by The Case of the Golden Idol: you have little vignettes where you are presented with items and information, and then you need to fill in the blanks in some text (à la madlibs) explaining what has happened in that scene. It’s pretty easy, pretty short, pretty funny. A decent couple-hours of fun, but not the most inspiring thing I’ve ever played.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-rise-of-the-golden-idol" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-rise-of-the-golden-idol">The Rise of the Golden Idol</h2>
<p>This is the sequel to The Case of the Golden Idol, one of my favorite games of 2022. This is still a very similar formula to that game: you are presented with a scene (or a series of scenes) and you poke around at it until you figure out what has transpired, and then you fill in the blanks: the name of the people involved, some text describing the actions that took place, and sometimes more involved (and more creative) things that I do not want to give away.</p>
<p>It is, by any aspect, a better game than the original, in my opinion, and also a more difficult one. It was extremely satisfying to slowly piece together what happens in every little bit of it, though! Chapter 4, in particular, is a delight, with two incredible puzzles (one of them is different from anything they had ever done and made me clap my hands in joy when I realized what was asked of me). It dragged on a <em>little</em> too long for my taste (the last couple scenarios are a bit too much), but I had an incredible time with it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="goldenidol.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="this game looks “ugly” in a way that I love"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/goldenidol.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="this game looks “ugly” in a way that I love"></a></p>
<figcaption>this game looks “ugly” in a way that I love</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="ufo-50" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ufo-50">UFO 50</h2>
<p>This has to be the best game of 2024, right? If I was to evaluate each of its 50 (!!!) constituent games on their own merits, a solid dozen would rank very highly in my game-of-the-year list. I went into it expecting to encounter small, largely arcade-y games, and maybe enjoy a handful of them (which I’d be more than happy with!). Instead, what I found were 50 <em>actual games</em>: yes, a few of them are fairly slight, many of them are pretty arcade-y. But after playing a little bit of every game, the list of games I wanted to go back to had… almost half of them.</p>
<p>Have I gone back to all of them? No, I haven’t. Have I gone back to <em>most</em> of them? Also no. But the idea that there are 20 great games there, just waiting for me to come back one day, is incredible. This game feels like a miracle; have you tried making 50 of <em>anything</em>? It’s a lot! They made 50 <em>games</em>. And they sold the whole package for, like, $25. I’ve never felt so much like I was ripping off a developer. It’s a wonderful thing, and I cannot recommend it enough.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ufo50.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="Pilot Quest is a ridiculous but wonderful idea for a game. You’ll need some meat."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/ufo50.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Pilot Quest is a ridiculous but wonderful idea for a game. You’ll need some meat."></a></p>
<figcaption>Pilot Quest is a ridiculous but wonderful idea for a game. You’ll need some meat.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="older-games-that-i-played-this-year" class="level1">
<h1>Older games that I played this year</h1>
<section id="boku-no-natsuyasumi-2" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="boku-no-natsuyasumi-2">Boku no Natsuyasumi 2</h2>
<p>I <a href="">wrote about that</a> already. Go read it! It’s a beautiful game.</p>
</section>
<section id="yakuza-3-4-5-6" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="yakuza-3-4-5-6">Yakuza 3, 4, 5, 6</h2>
<p>Yes. all of these. Is Yakuza formulaic? Yes, very much so. Is the combat kinda whatever? Absolutely. But there’s very few things in life I enjoy more than seeying Kazuma Kiryu and the goofballs he surrounds himself with doing some goofball stuff. These games wouldn’t work without the weird tonal shifts from super-serious-crime-drama main story and outright comedy in the side stories. They wouldn’t work if Kazuma Kiryu wasn’t the most kind-hearted head-empty dude in the world (which is why a lot of 4 and 5 don’t work super well for me). These games are a few slips away from being forgettable or actively disagreeable, and yet they manage to toe the line just right. I love them. (Yakuza 6 is the best of the bunch.)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="onomichio.webp" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Ono Michio forever."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/onomichio.webp" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Ono Michio forever."></a></p>
<figcaption>Ono Michio forever.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="live-a-live" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="live-a-live">Live-a-Live</h2>
<p>This shot up very high on my list of favorite JRPGs ever. Not everything hits (I find the meta/overarching narrative pretty meh, and some of the genre stuff it’s doing is pretty rote), but it’s so creative, so different from most other stuff in that space, so well-crafted. If you like JRPGs and you don’t know much about Live-a-Live, I would just go and play it sight unseen. It’s a good time.</p>
</section>
<section id="contradiction-spot-the-liar" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="contradiction-spot-the-liar">Contradiction: Spot the Liar</h2>
<p>Ok, hear me out: murder mystery adventure game. FMV. Cheesy acting. Quaint English village that might be harboring a cult. Interested yet? What if I did… THIS</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yuTJQ3wTx3M?si=Lz9SOsS5PjW1-wBS&amp;t=60" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>(go to 1:00 in the video if timestamp doesn’t work)</p>
<p>Anyway, Contradiction is not a <em>good</em> game, but it’s a lot of fun, and I enjoyed it enough to put together a speedrun just because I could.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>video games</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-2024-games/ufo50.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>BINA Community Congress and Northeast Bioimage Analysis Meeting round-up</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-11-21-conference-roundup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="so-i-went-to-a-couple-more-conferences." class="level1">
<h1>So I went to a couple more conferences.</h1>
<p>Before anything else, I have to thank <a href="https://www.bioimagingnorthamerica.org/">BINA</a> for financial support getting me to their Community Congress AND for providing travel grants for folks coming to the NE Bioimage Analysis Meeting!</p>
<p>It’s been a couple months, I know, I know, but I still want to recap the BINA Congress in September, and then I’m going to talk about a meeting we organized in our <a href="https://www.jax.org">JAX</a> campus.</p>
</section>
<section id="bina-community-congress-2024" class="level1">
<h1>BINA Community Congress 2024</h1>
<p>So in September 23-26th a bunch of imaging folks from the US, Canada and Mexico (somehow we always end up talking about them in this order…) made their way to Madison, WI for the <a href="https://www.bioimagingnorthamerica.org/events/bina-2024-community-congress/">BINA Community Congress 2024</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="PXL_20240926_223010798.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Madison is beautiful!"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-11-21-conference-roundup/PXL_20240926_223010798.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Madison is beautiful!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Madison is beautiful!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="so-what-is-this-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-what-is-this-meeting">So what is this meeting?</h2>
<p>It is a question I had going in. This was my first time attending a BINA meeting in person, and looking at the schedule beforehand it felt a bit… I don’t want to sound negative because, as you will see, my feelings coming out of it were very positive, but navel-gaze-y? Most sessions seemed to be individual BINA working groups giving updates on what they have been doing, then a few keynotes, and that was most of the schedule.</p>
<p>I was very, very happy to be completely wrong about it. It became very clear quickly that yes, this is a pretty tight-knit community, but one that is open and welcoming. Each working group had full freedom to do whatever they wanted with the session allocated to it; a couple gave work updates, others gave the space for individual people to give talks, there were multiple panel discussions. It was much more varied and productive than I was expecting, and genuinely very good.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-worked-well" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-worked-well">What worked well?</h2>
<p>Well, I just talked a bit about the schedule itself; I think giving working groups freedom to use their time as they saw fit was a big plus. Generally, I found the schedule extremely good: sessions were 1:30 at most, and we never had multiple sessions back-to-back. That kept people energized and meant there were plenty of breaks, which is both beneficial in terms of keeping an engaged audience and in making it clear that this was a conference structured around getting people talking to each other. That was emphasized by the long lunch breaks and breaks between the last session of the day and dinner. At this point, I think any in-person meeting should have such a focus; we can watch talks from home, but face time is scarce and should be maximized.</p>
<p>We had some excellent keynotes, such as Eric Betzig giving a talk honoring his late friend Mike Davidson and my good buddy Virginie Uhlmann from the <a href="https://www.biovisioncenter.uzh.ch/">BioVisionCenter</a> in Zurich. We had my other good buddy <a href="https://www.broadinstitute.org/bios/beth-cimini">Beth Cimini</a> accepting the inaugural <a href="https://www.bioimagingnorthamerica.org/michael-w-davidson-memorial-award-2024/">Mike Davidson Memorial Award</a> (which she thoroughly deserves!). We had multiple dinners at the waterfront. Overall I had a fantastic time meeting old friends, reconnecting with folks I hadn’t seen in a while, meeting folks I only knew from the Internet for the first time, and making completely new connections that are already paying off.</p>
<p>Speaking of: this meeting used an online platform for its program and attendees list that included an online chat capability, and I found that extremely useful. First, knowing who would be there made me mentally establish a list of folks I should go talk to, and second because I had a couple of people reaching out to me via online chat before the conference asking for a chance to connect in person during the meeting, which made me go out of my way to find those people and engage with them. Highly recommend for other meetings!</p>
</section>
<section id="so-what-could-be-better" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-what-could-be-better">So what could be better?</h2>
<p>Honestly? Not much. I think my one “room for improvement” note is that working groups felt like they were all doing their own thing despite obvious areas of overlap between them, where they could be working together. Whether that should be achieved by overlap in membership between groups or by having cross-group meetings and activities I am not sure, but I would love to see more of that! (spoilers: the nature of the 2025 meeting might force teams to have cross-group sessions, which is a good first step.)</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>If you are interested in what happened there, every single session was recorded and is available in this <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLG5nZ7mF_r1pspbfoTObNRy1-9n1h15ZM&amp;si=maQ-xt-fd6IuxViG">youtube playlist</a>. There’s a lot of good stuff in there!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="PXL_20240923_173935704-1536x568.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="Photo courtesy of BINA - if you can find me there, you win a prize. (I struggled to find myself, and I knew where I was standing.)"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-11-21-conference-roundup/PXL_20240923_173935704-1536x568.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Photo courtesy of BINA - if you can find me there, you win a prize. (I struggled to find myself, and I knew where I was standing.)"></a></p>
<figcaption>Photo courtesy of BINA - if you can find me there, you win a prize. (I struggled to find myself, and I knew where I was standing.)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="northeast-bioimage-analysis-meeting-2024" class="level1">
<h1>Northeast Bioimage Analysis Meeting 2024</h1>
<p>This one’s way fresher in my mind (happened last week!) and way closer to my heart (I’m one of the organizers! It happens in our campus!).</p>
<section id="so-what-is-this-meeting-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-what-is-this-meeting-1">So what is this meeting?</h2>
<p>When I moved to the US five years ago, I felt very lonely. Professionally, I mean. Two years inside the rich bioimage analysis community in the UK (and in Europe more generally) spoiled me, and discovering there was no regular bioimage analysis meeting in the US, no support network, no structured community of practice, was a big blow. All of sudden it made sense that I kept running into people from the US at every bioimage analysis meeting in Europe…</p>
<p>Skip forward a couple years and a few folks at JAX plus the aforementioned Beth Cimini and the suddenly-based-in-the-US Simon Noerrelykke from the <a href="https://iac.hms.harvard.edu/">Image Analysis Collaboratory</a> at Harvard Medical School decided enough is enough: if no one organizes a US-based bioimage analysis meeting, we might as well do it ourselves. So we did it: initially with a focus on the Northeast US and trying to establish a sense of local community in the area, we ran our first meeting in 2023. It was a single day, around 30-35 people showed up, it was great.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.jax.org/education-and-learning/education-calendar/2024/11-november/northeast-bioimage-analysis-meeting">This year we went bigger</a>: a two-day meeting. Many invited speakers. Charging participation fees. And so we get to…</p>
</section>
<section id="what-worked-well-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-worked-well-1">What worked well?</h2>
<p>I think we put together an outstanding list of speakers, both invited and abstract submissions. Given that we did not have a travel budget for invited speakers, a few of these talks were virtual, yes, but the average level of talks was extremely high, with many leading names in the area giving talks about their work. We got new people to attend the meeting, meet each other, have conversations with other folks working in similar positions elsewhere.</p>
<p>And that was the main focus of this meeting: community and connections. We scheduled plenty of “downtime” to allow for conversations to blossom, and that was a success. I met many people I didn’t know, and I was the one inviting speakers! I think it was a huge success both in terms of networking and in pure scientific terms. We even dragged, I mean, <em>gently invited</em> folks for dinner at <a href="https://parkvillemarket.com/">Parkville Market</a>, which folks seemed to enjoy a lot.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="44dfeb9e-1d8f-402d-b60d-fe50813fbcdb_720.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="Talley Lambert himself graced us with his presence! I had never met Talley before this."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-11-21-conference-roundup/44dfeb9e-1d8f-402d-b60d-fe50813fbcdb_720.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Talley Lambert himself graced us with his presence! I had never met Talley before this."></a></p>
<figcaption>Talley Lambert himself graced us with his presence! I had never met Talley before this.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-could-be-better" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-could-be-better">What could be better?</h2>
<p>Well, this is a… small meeting. We had 20-25 people in person, plus a handful online. Which is about half of what I’d like this meeting to be. A bit of that was unfortunate scheduling (a large imaging meeting was scheduled for conflicting dates after we had already announced ours!), some of it is that we’re still not reaching the people we’d like to reach, some of it is that we’d probably get more people if this meeting was in Boston. Still work to do.</p>
<p>Organizing an event is exhausting. This year was mainly on my shoulders (with help from the Education team at JAX), and it was STRESSFUL. Organizing this every year at JAX is just not feasible without me losing years of my lifespan. So we need to think about what this looks like long-term.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts-1">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>This is a good meeting! I wish more people joined us! I think it would benefit everyone! I had a great time and seeing people interacting and having fruitful conversations is extremely rewarding as an organizer. I had a great time meeting new people, and seeing familiar faces. I think we are slowly creating a bit more of a sense of community in the area, and that’s great.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>BINA</category>
  <category>Northeast</category>
  <category>Bioimaging</category>
  <category>Conference</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-11-21-conference-roundup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-11-21-conference-roundup/bina-logo.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="54" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My August project: Boku no Natsuyasumi 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="playing-boku-no-natsuyasumi-2-every-single-day-in-august-has-been-a-delight." class="level1">
<h1>Playing Boku no Natsuyasumi 2 every single day in August has been a delight.</h1>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-04 19_12_51-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Meeting people is hard."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-04 19_12_51-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Meeting people is hard."></a></p>
<figcaption>Meeting people is hard.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you’ve never heard of Boku no Natsuyasumi (My Summer Vacation): it’s a very popular series of games in Japan, where the basic premise is that you are a young child going to spend your (titular) summer vacation somewhere. You can think of it as Animal Crossing-adjacent: you explore a cute location, interact with the people living there, catch some fish and some bugs, and so on. There’s a day-night cycle, certain things are only available at certain times, you know the drill.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-28 15_08_17-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="The Akane house in Fumi became my second residence for August."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-28 15_08_17-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The Akane house in Fumi became my second residence for August."></a></p>
<figcaption>The Akane house in Fumi became my second residence for August.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>None of the Bokunatsu games saw a western release, ever. (the newer stuff from the same studio, Millenium Kitchen, is available, though.) It’s one of those series that people who are deep enough into the rabbit hole that is gaming talked about without full context, and western folks who can speak Japanese raved about. And then, a group of <em>extremely</em> dedicated fans carefully put together an English translation of Bokunatsu 2. I cannot say enough glowing things about the work they’ve done here, both in terms of the quality of the prose itself and the absolute technical marvel that this translation is. For example, the original game has vertical text; they somehow converted that into a horizontal textbox at the bottom of the screen.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-07 14_44_04-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-3" title="You do get to open this gate if you want to."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-07 14_44_04-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="You do get to open this gate if you want to."></a></p>
<figcaption>You do get to open this gate if you want to.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ll get this out of the way: Boku no Natsuyasumi 2 is wonderful. It’s a small miracle. It’s warm, gentle, thoughtful, and just a tiny little bit sappy at times. It made me feel nostalgic for rural Japan in the 70s, a time and space I had very little knowledge about.</p>
<p>So the game starts and it’s August 1st, 1975. You’re a 9-year old kid named Boku (I know), taking the ferry to Fumi, a tiny little community somewhere in Japan. Your mom is about to give birth to a child, and your parents sent you over to stay with your aunt and uncle in Fumi so you don’t need to be around for that. That’s it. This is all you’re given. There are no objectives, no tutorials, nothing you need to do. You’re a kid on vacation, staying in a small village with your extended family and the locals. Have fun. You’ll have breakfast and dinner with your family at set times, and you have a limit for your bed time. Those are the only limitations.</p>
<p>I love how open-ended everything is. There were many things that I’ve certainly missed, some things I only discovered when it was too late to do them properly, and so on. It’s a game that clearly doesn’t expect you to see everything in a single playthrough, and getting rid of that minmaxing bug in your brain is a good thing here. In just a few in-game days, I was able to let go of the instinct to optimize and just enjoy being a weird kid running around this village.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-31 16_42_22-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-4" title="I genuinely have no idea if this scene always happens or if some of the stuff I did made it happen."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-31 16_42_22-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="I genuinely have no idea if this scene always happens or if some of the stuff I did made it happen."></a></p>
<figcaption>I genuinely have no idea if this scene always happens or if some of the stuff I did made it happen.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Boku is a wonderful protagonist - the way this kid is written and voiced made me smile all the time. Boku is a kind-hearted, curious, very funny kid, who asks good questions and likes teasing people. But he’s very much a kid. He doesn’t understand some things even when you, the player, does; there’s nothing you can do in-game to change that. You are not Boku.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-10 18_21_48-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-5" title="Gramps had some stuff to take off his chest."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-10 18_21_48-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Gramps had some stuff to take off his chest."></a></p>
<figcaption>Gramps had some stuff to take off his chest.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Now for some added fun: as I said, this is a game that starts on August 1st, 1975. Following a friend’s suggestion, I decided to play one in-game day per real-life day. It didn’t end up mapping one to one for a number of reasons, but I did my best. I know there’s no such thing as the right way to play a game but honestly? This might be the right way to play this game. If you’re in the northern hemisphere. And you live in a place with seasons. The reminders that summer is ending in-game synchronizing with the first slightly chillier days where I am worked really, really well. Everyone’s mood shifts as fall is starting to peek around the corner: the people in the game and myself. It also helps that each day takes about half an hour if you’re playing on the default speed. It’s a totally reasonable time commitment for a daily task, right there with my crosswords.</p>
<p>The one thing I’m divided on is whether to do this again next year. One one hand, I would love to go back to Fumi, see the things I didn’t see, do the things I didn’t do. But at the same time, I love where Boku’s story ended at. This month of August felt like <em>my</em> version of what Boku’ August would have been, and to some degree going back to it would just undermine its power by making me optimize more, focus less on enjoying the scenery and the people in the village. Ultimately, I worry that re-experiencing August 1975 would make this month less unique.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="2024-08-12 11_36_36-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-6" title="Boku loves to sit at a place and just vibe."><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/2024-08-12 11_36_36-ぼくのなつやすみ2 海の冒険篇.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Boku loves to sit at a place and just vibe."></a></p>
<figcaption>Boku <em>loves</em> to sit at a place and just vibe.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>video games</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-08-31-boku-no-natsuyasumi2/bokunonatsu2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>OME Community Meeting 2024 round-up</title>
  <dc:creator>Erick Ratamero</dc:creator>
  <link>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="ome-community-meeting-2024---what-happened-there" class="level1">
<h1>OME Community Meeting 2024 - what happened there?</h1>
<p>So as a first real blogpost I decided it was a good idea to write a quick recap/summary of what happened during the <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/events/ome-community-meeting-2024/">OME 2024 Community Meeting</a> - it’s both a pretty easy write for me and potentially helpful for other folks out there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="PXL_20240529_073549219.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1" title="Did you know there’s a Lemmings statue in Dundee?"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/PXL_20240529_073549219.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Did you know there’s a Lemmings statue in Dundee?"></a></p>
<figcaption>Did you know there’s a Lemmings statue in Dundee?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="so-what-is-this-meeting" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-what-is-this-meeting">So what is this meeting?</h2>
<p>Probably a good place to start is explaining <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/index.html">OME</a> - according to themselves,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>a consortium of universities, research labs, industry and developers producing open-source software and format standards for microscopy data.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In practice, it’s a community of like-minded tool developers who write things that are 1) open-source; 2) dealing with microscopy data; 3) uses the <a href="https://ome-model.readthedocs.io/en/stable/">OME data model</a> to some degree - and the users of such tools. In the past (i.e.&nbsp;pre-pandemic), this was a relatively large meeting (100-200 people is my guess?), with lots of end-users presenting their use cases.</p>
<p>Post-pandemic, this survived in a kinda-barebones, virtual-only format for a few years, until May this year, when we finally managed to meet in person again, in lovely Dundee, Scotland. Even better, I was invited to give a talk! (for the record, this is the second time ever I had an proper invited talk, and the first time I managed to be there to actually give it.). Though much smaller than previous meetings (attendance was around 45 people), most of the big names are core developers were there.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="PXL_20240528_100142225.PANO.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" title="the day before the conference, I climbed a hill"><img src="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/PXL_20240528_100142225.PANO.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="the day before the conference, I climbed a hill"></a></p>
<figcaption>the day before the conference, I climbed a hill</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="now-a-quick-recap-per-day" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="now-a-quick-recap-per-day">Now a quick recap per day</h2>
<section id="day-0-speakers-dinner" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-0-speakers-dinner">Day 0: speakers’ dinner</h3>
<p>So the day before the actual meeting, the people giving invited talks had the chance to have dinner together - it’s the kind of informal opportunity to network and enjoy each other’s company that is really hard to replicate virtually, and after 5 years without in-person meetings, it was great to see many familiar faces! We also had a LOT of tapas. I did not take pictures, so you’ll have to believe me.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-1-bioimage-data-resources-and-community" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-1-bioimage-data-resources-and-community">Day 1: BioImage Data Resources and Community</h3>
<p>This was the main “conference day” - invited talks from all over the world, about how institutions and cross-institutional entities are involved in the OME ecosystem. This is where we (i.e.&nbsp;The Jackson Laboratory folks) gave our invited talk, and essential projects around OME (such as <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/bio-formats/">Bio-formats</a> and the <a href="https://idr.openmicroscopy.org/">IDR</a> gave community updates.</p>
<p>The big takeaway in my opinion was that large national entities, such as German Bioimaging, France Bioimaging and NL-Bioimaging, are deeptly invested in OME. Similarly, large public data repositories also rely heavily on the tools the data models of the OME environment; not only the IDR, but also things like the Bioimage Archive and SSBD. These entities have a mix of either centralized and distributed infrastructure, and very different ideas for what metadata standards should look like, making harmonization between these disparate cases pretty hard.</p>
<p>Still, some common themes have emerged, such as the <em>desire</em> to have common metadata standards, and a convergence towards using OME-Zarr as the file format for the future. We are seeing, for example, multiple efforts for processing OME-Zarr using Slurm/HPC have emerged (such as the awesome <a href="https://fractal-analytics-platform.github.io/">Fractal</a>). The day ended with very good food (you’ll start to sense a theme here) at <a href="https://www.dca.org.uk/experience-dca/eat-and-drink-at-jute/">Dundee Contemporary Arts</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-2-training-on-omero-and-workshops" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-2-training-on-omero-and-workshops">Day 2: Training on OMERO and Workshops</h3>
<p>For the first half of day 2, we had a few more talks, focusing on using <a href="https://www.openmicroscopy.org/omero/">OMERO</a> in training settings - it included an initially funny, but then just awesome story about a collaboration with an Indonesian university, which was unwittingly “abusing” the demo OMERO server provided by the University of Dundee to teach pathology classes to medical students. The “abuse” was discovered and, instead of just cutting them off, a partnership was developed, and now Dundee hosts a separate server for the Indonesian folks.</p>
<p>The second half of day 2 was dedicated to workshops - we had breakout rooms with a few scheduled sessions, and an extra room for impromptu/ad-hoc sessions. The sessions I attended had a lot of Zarr talk, including the first discussions of a “Dundee Pledge” - an attempt to align the folks in the room around a set of practices and tools that would allow for easily extensible metadata. Again, the day ended with excellent food - this time, at an Indian place whose name escapes me right now.</p>
</section>
<section id="day-3-unmeeting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="day-3-unmeeting">Day 3: Unmeeting</h3>
<p>Day 3 was a half-day, scheduled to end at lunchtime. It was “organized” as an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference">unmeeting</a> - participants decided what the agenda of day 3 would be at the beginning of the day. What ended up happening was a lot of work and discussion around what eventually became the <a href="https://forum.image.sc/t/ome2024-ngff-challenge/97363">OME2024 NGFF Challenge</a>.</p>
<p>So what is that? In brief, in Josh Moore’s words,</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>converting some significant corpus of day (e.g., 1 PB) using what we think the next version of OME-Zarr (e.g., including sharding, collections, etc.) will be by the end of September.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s an ambitious plan: it involves fast-forwarding some specifications in a pretty speculative way, coordinating multiple entities and institutions, and herding cats in a very short timeframe. The plan is to, very quickly, demonstrate that this is a viable way of going in the future, and speed up tool development in some areas. Excitingly, since as part of the challenge multiple institutions agree on a (<em>very</em>) minimal metadata standard, that means a single front-end can index and search data that exists in many different storage sources, paving the way for a future where public data repositories can be fully federated.</p>
<p>Since then, multiple working groups have made quick progress, and in two days we are hitting the date where specifications for the challenge will enter a freeze. That will give people time to get their tooling in order, and to actually convert the data they will provide for the challenge. Needless to say, we at JAX will be taking part in it, planning to offer around 50TB of Zarr files to it.</p>
<p>I am told this day ended with a scotch tasting - I had an early plane to catch and ended up skipping it.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-about-next-year" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-about-next-year">What about next year?</h3>
<p>The idea is to continue in-person meetings for next year - folks in the US have soft-committed to organizing it this side of the pond next year. We’re still looking for a location (probably on the East Coast), but there’s already work being done towards that!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>I think it’s fair to say this was the most <em>intense</em> (and probably the best) scientific meeting I have ever attended - the fact that this is very much the niche where I spend most of my time, and the relatively small size of the meeting, meant that every waking hour was spent having meaningful, important discussions. You’d go for breakfast and other folks would be there, already talking shop. Then you’d spend the whole day at the conference, then have dinner at the conference, then go grab drinks with the conference folks. Of course, there was plenty of time for less-professional talk as well, but but you still had to be “on”. I am VERY excited for next year already - especially if it ends up being in our backyard!</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>OME</category>
  <category>OMERO</category>
  <category>Conference</category>
  <category>work</category>
  <guid>https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://erickmartins.github.io/posts/2024-07-29-ome-meeting-roundup/ome-logomark.svg" medium="image" type="image/svg+xml"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
